Guide to the Federal Theatre Project Collection, 1936-1939 CTC.1979.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Federal Theatre Project Collection
1936-1939
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Federal Theatre Project (U.S.)
CTC.1979.02
5 Linear Feet (12 document boxes)
The Federal Theatre Project was a New Deal initiative established in 1935 within the Work Projects Administration (WPA). It aimed to provide employment for out-of-work theatre professionals including actors, writers, directors, and designers. Under the dynamic direction of Hallie Flanagan, the project encouraged experimental work in theatres across the country and also staged revivals of European and American classics in regional theatres, attracting large new theatre audiences as a result. The left-leaning political tone of some of the plays drew the attention of the House on Un-American Activities Committee, which prompted an investigation of the Federal Theatre Project that led to its dissolution on July 30, 1939. The Federal Theatre Project Collection includes publications, reports, and programs that reflect the activities of the project between the years of 1936-1939.
History
The Federal Theatre Project was a New Deal initiative established in 1935 within the Work Projects Administration (WPA). Under President Franklin Delano Roosevelt's Administration, the Federal Theatre Project aimed to provide employment for out-of-work theatre professionals including actors, writers, directors, and designers during the Great Depression as well as reinvigorating theatre and providing entertainment for a despondent nation.
Under the dynamic direction of Hallie Flanagan, the project encouraged experimental, uncensored, and unrestricted work in theatres across the country and also staged revivals of European and American classics in regional theatres, attracting large new theatre audiences as a result. The plays often reflected current events and controversial issues such as farm-aid policy, syphilis testing, and housing inequity and were extremely popular with audiences. The left leaning political tone of some of the plays drew the attention of the House on Un-American Activities Committee, which prompted an investigation of the Federal Theatre Project that led to its dissolution on July 30, 1939.
The Federal Theatre Project Collection includes publications, reports, and programs that reflect the activities of the project between the years of 1936-1939. The Federal Theatre Project was the first and only initiative of its' kind instituted by the Federal Government to execute the production and administration of theatre on a national scale. Consequently, this program introduced European epic theatre to new audiences never before exposed to live performance and was instrumental in creating socially significant and influential works.
Scope and Content Notes
The Federal Theatre Project Collection consists of various Federal Theatre Project materials such as scripts, programs, reports, and meeting agendas dating between 1935 and 1939. The collection offers a variety of information reflecting the administrative, legal, operational, and live performance activities of the Federal Theatre Project.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Federal Theatre Project Collection, 1936-1939, CTC.1979.02, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Federal Theatre Project Collection, 1935-1939, CTC.03, The Ford E. and Harriet R. Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
The following two journal titles are a part of the journal holdings of the Curtis Theatre Collection:
Federal Theatre Bulletin: v. 1, no. 2, 5, 6; v.2, no. 1-4 [currently in process of being catalogued].
The Living Newspaper: v. 1. no. 1-3; v.2, no. 1; v. 3, no. 1; v. 5, no. 5, 9, 18 [currently in process of being catalogued].
Custodial History
The Federal Theatre Project Collection was under the stewardship of the New York Public Library until it was gifted to the Special Collections Department at the University of Pittsburgh in 1979.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the New York Public Library in 1979.
Arrangement
The Federal Theatre Project Collection is arranged by the following series:
Series I. National Service Bureau publications, 1936-1939
Series II. Reports, 1938
Series III. Programs
Theater and state -- United States -- 20th century; Theater and society -- United States -- 20th century; Theater programs; Bibliographies; Newspapers; Newsletters; Scripts (Documents); Living newspaper; Theater -- United States; Experimental theater -- United States; Performing arts -- United States; National Service Bureau (U.S.); Federal Theatre Project (U.S.) -- History; Federal Theatre Project (U.S.)
- National Service Bureau publications, 1936-1939; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series of National Service Bureau publications includes bibliographies, synopses with production notes, and play scripts covering political, ethnic, holiday, historical, religious, children's and marionette plays. The National Service Bureau was officially established in 1937 by combining the Federal Theatre Project's Play Bureau and Play Policy Board. The National Service Bureau was headquartered in New York City where it supported regional Federal Theatre Project units by providing research material, consultation services, and publications such as those found within this series.
  - Anglo-Jewish Full Length Plays in English and Yiddish, January 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anti-war Plays, Anglo-Jewish Part 2 in Yiddish, July 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anti-war Plays, Foreign and Anglo-Jewish Lists, October 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anti-war Plays for Community Theatres, October 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anti-war Plays, Royalty List, November 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Barnum Returns or The New American Museum, May 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - A Bibliography of Marionette Plays, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brother Mose, A Comedy of Negro Life with Music and Spirituals, September 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Better Sort or A Girl of Spirit: An Operatical, Comical Farce, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Catholic Plays, Part 1: For Advanced Groups, November 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Catholic Plays, Part 2 and 3: For Intermediate and Junior Groups, February 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Children's Operettas, June 1937 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Children's Plays (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Children of Salem, January 1938 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Christmas Plays, November 1936 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Copy of Card File of Commercial Phonograph Recordings on Deposit at the Archive of American Folk Song, February 1937 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Disappointment or The Force of Credulity, May 1938 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Death Takes the Wheel, Adapted for Buffalo Historical Marionette Theatre (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Donogoo, September 1937 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Don Quixote, Adapted for the Marionette Theatre, July 1937 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Dragon Znee Zee, A Play for Chinese Marionettes, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Early Spanish One-act Plays in English Translation (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Easter Plays: Biblical Dramas, Modern Dramas, Service Dramas for Churches and Schools, March 1937 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 50 Non-royalty Plays, Part 1: One-act Plays, October 1936 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 50 Non-royalty Plays, Part 2: Full-length Plays, April 1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 59 Monologues, December 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 56 Minstrels, February 1938 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - The First Comic Opera in America, November 1935 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Full Length Plays, October 1936 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Haven or The Merited Gallows, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Highlights of the First Production Conference of the New York City Unit of the Federal Theatre, July 1936 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - His Majesty the Microbe or The Microbe Universe, a Marionette Play in No Acts with Ten Scenes (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Holy Night, October 1938 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Injunction Granted, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Injunction Granted, July 1937 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Irish Plays, August 1938 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - It Can't Happen Here, September 1936 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Jellico an' de Critters (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Jewish Non-royalty Plays and Pageants: Holiday, Historical, General, January 1937 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - John Henry, Steel-driving Man, January 1938 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Juvenile Operettas, Part 2, May 1938 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Katcha and the Devil, July 1938 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Late Primitive, July 1937 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Lists of Little Known One-act Plays, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - List of Negro Plays, March 1938 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - The Little Crab, November 1937 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - The Lost Generation, A Play about Youth, July 1937 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Lucy Moore, the Prune Hater's Daughter (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - The Man of the Times or A Scarcity of Cash (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - A Modern Miscellany (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Morning Paper, A Play about Newsboys, July 1937 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The Most Wicked Pirate, September 1937 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Mr. Cold, You Can't Catch Me, September 1937 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Musical Plays, December 1936 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Nathan Hale, A Marionette Play in 5 Scenes, June 1937 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - National Play Bureau Publications: A Catalog, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Nativity, November 1937 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Negro Plays (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Nelagony, November 1937 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - 1935, 1936-1938 (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
  - 90 New Plays, December 1936 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - No More Peace (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Non-royalty Plays for Halloween, Thanksgiving, Plymouth Days, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Oliver Twist, Adapted for Marionettes, July 1937 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - One-act Negro Plays, October 1936 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - One-act Plays of Moliere (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - One Third of a Nation, Volume 1, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
  - One Third of a Nation, Volume 2, April 1938 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Operettas, November 1938 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - The Pagent of the Sherman and the Tailors, October 1937 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Patriotic Plays Non-royalty, Part 1: Abraham Lincoln, George Washington, January 1937 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Patriotic Plays Non-royalty, Part 2: Memorial Day, Flag Day, Fourth of July, April 1937 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Plays Available for Amateur Production (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Plays Suggested for Consideration by the Federal Theatre Project (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Power, September 1937 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Precious Laura, February 1937 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Prologue to Glory, May 1938 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Puppet Teaching, Weekly News Bulletin: v.1, no. 1; v.2, no.1. Additional copies of v. 1, no. 12, 14, 15, 17, June 1937-January 1938 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - R.U.R., Adapted for the Marionette Theatre (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Rural Plays, Part 1: Dramas, Comedies, Tragedies, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Rural Plays, Part 2: Dramas, Comedies, Farces, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Rural Plays, Part 3: Drama, Comedy, Farce and Burlesque, Pageant, Collections, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Russian Plays: A Preliminary Catalogue (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Sancho Panza (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Series of Children's Non-royalty Plays, Part 1: Health, Safety, Humane, December 1936 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - 72 Vaudeville Sketches Non-royalty, Part 1, July 1937 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - 72 Vaudeville Sketches Non-royalty, Part 2, March 1938 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Sherlock Holmes, Adapted for Marionettes in Four Scenes, July 1937 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Some Irish Plays, April 1937 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Some New Unpublished One-act Plays Royalty Plays, Part 1, July 1937 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Spanish Miracles and Moralities Available in English Translation (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Spirochete, January 1939 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Suggested Production List of 15 One-act Negro Plays (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Suggested Production List of Non-royalty Christmas Plays, Part 1: Children's Plays Secular, November 1936 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Suggested Production List of Non-royalty Plays, Part 1: One-act Plays, October 1936 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Suggested Production List of Non-royalty Plays, Part 2: Full-length Plays, October 1936 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Suggested Production List of Plays for a Marionette Theatre (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Suggested Repertory of American, English, and Irish Plays (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Suggested Repertory of Classic English Plays (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Suggested Repertory of Modern Continental Plays (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Theatre Technique No. 3: Puppets and Masks, December 1937 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 34 Old and New Spanish Plays, January 1937 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Threnody-American, A Radio Drama about Youth, June 1937 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Toby Tyler with the Circus, July 1938 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - The Totem (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Triple-A Plowed Under, 1936-1938 (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
  - Treasure Island, November 1938 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - 22 English Mysteries, Miracles, Moralities, April 1937 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - The Valiant Little Tailor, July 1938 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - We Are the Future, A Play of Rural Youth, July 1937 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - We Produce a Puppet Show (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - The Wildcats, A Play about Youth, July 1937 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - WPA Circus, The Route Book for the 1937 Season of the WPA Circus (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Reports, 1938; II.
  This series reflects the administrative and operational activities of the Federal Theatre Project through reports and meeting agendas.
  - First Federal Summer Theatre...A Report, 1938 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Summary of Federal Theatre Activities, September 1938 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - National Policy Board: Agenda, April 12-14, 1938 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - National Policy Board: Agenda, August 11-13, 1938 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Programs, III.
  This series consists of the programs of Federal Theatre Project productions. They mostly reflect performances in the New York City region and are undated.
  - Programs A-D (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Adelante, 1.
    - American Holiday, 2.
    - Androcles and the Lion, 3.
    - Die Apostel (The Apostles), 4.
    - Arms and the Man, 5.
    - Around the Corner, 6.
    - Around the World in 80 Days, 7.
    - Backwash, 8.
    - The Ballad of Davy Crockett, 9.
    - The Barker, 10.
    - Bassa Moona, 11.
    - The Bat, 12.
    - Battle Hymn, 13.
    - Big Blow, 14.
    - Chalk Dust, 15.
    - Chamber Opera in English, 16.
    - The Chocolate Soldier, 17.
    - The Christmas Carol, 18.
    - Class of '29, 19.
    - Community Sing, 20.
    - Coriolanus, 21.
    - The Cradle Will Rock, 22.
    - Craig's Wife, 23.
    - The Dance of Death, 24.
    - The Dark Tower, 25.
    - The Devil Passes, 26.
    - The Devil's Disciple, 27.
    - Doctor Faustus, 28.
    - Double Door, 29.
  - Programs E-H (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - The Emperor's New Clothes, 1.
    - An Enemy of the People, 2.
    - The Eternal Prodigal, 3.
    - Eugene O'Neill's One-Act Plays of the Sea, 4.
    - Excursion, 5.
    - The Farmer's Wife, 6.
    - The First Legion, 7.
    - Flight, 8.
    - Four American One-Act Plays, 9.
    - Haiti, 10.
    - Help Yourself!, 11.
    - A Hero is Born, 12.
    - Holy Night, 13.
    - Horse Eats Hat, 14.
    - Horse Play, 15.
    - How Long Brethren?, 16.
  - Programs I-M (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - In Heaven and Earth, 1.
    - In Praise of Husbands, 2.
    - Iolanthe, 3.
    - It Can't Happen Here, 4.
    - Jefferson Davis, 5.
    - Life and Death of an American, 6.
    - The Lights o' London, 7.
    - Love in Humble Life, 8.
    - Macbeth, 9.
    - The Mikado, 10.
    - Mr. Jiggins of Jigginstown, 11.
    - Murder in the Cathedral, 12.
  - Programs N-P (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Native Ground, 1.
    - New York Civic Orchestra, 2.
    - Noah, 3.
    - On the Rocks, 4.
    - The Path of Flowers, 5.
    - Pinocchio, 6.
    - Pins & Needles, 7.
    - The Playboy of the Western World, 8.
    - Processional, 9.
    - Professor Mamlock, 10.
    - Prologue to Glory, 11.
  - Programs Q-S (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Repertory of Important Plays, 1.
    - The Shanghai Sal, 2.
    - The Shining Hour, 3.
    - Showing Off, 4.
    - Sing for Your Supper, 5.
    - The Solitaire Man, 6.
    - Spirochete, 7.
    - Spread Eagle, 8.
    - Street Scene, 9.
    - The Sun and I, 10.
    - Sweet Land, 11.
    - Swing It, 12.
    - The Swing Mikado, 13.
    - Swing Parade, 14.
  - Programs T-Z (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - The Tailor Becomes a Store Keeper, 1.
    - Take It or Leave It, 2.
    - Tamed and How, 3.
    - The Tavern, 4.
    - Ten Minute Alibi, 5.
    - Three One Act Plays, 6.
    - Treasure Island, 7.
    - The Trial of Doctor Beck, 8.
    - Trojan Incident, 9.
    - Turpentine, 10.
    - Twelfth Night, 11.
    - Two-A-Day, 12.
    - Unto Such Glory and Hymn to the Rising Sun, 13.
    - A Woman of Destiny, 14.